This movement will once again have a growth force,
we are only going to take the epiblastic tissue.
I have cells that are upwards, in divergence,
and here, the same ones that are directed towards convergence.
So, cells that are in a dome of expansion,
and others that are in a dome of retention.
So I have cells that are in convexity,
and cells that are in concavity.
And what do we observe again?
That the algorithm intervenes again there.
We notice that the cells that are placed in the front part
will develop much faster than the cells that are in the back.
And we notice that there is a support point here.
I have little growth here.
If I add on my embryo with more details,
so here I already have...
The head, cranial, cranio, caudal, which is outlined from the moment I have a creation
of a film.
Below, what do I have? I have another layer of cells.
Yes, but within my polarity, I have two things that occur in
the tissue.
You can see this in the speed, the growth.
It's that the ectodermic tissue has always consumed faster than the tissue
below.
It's the one that takes the information the fastest, from the get-go, just from
the implantation.
So the cells that are here, let's say these are the endoblastic cells
that will follow the movement,
but not in the same way, because they don't have the same reference,
not the same development and not the same spatio-temporal information
and energy.
They don't have the same geolocation information.
Thus, we find that the cells that are here will develop faster.
So there is a point we call point zero.
In the wave, you see, in the wave, you have this almost motionless point, as we call it.
I place it in a growth process, meaning I draw it like this.
We start from above.
Here, this is the time, this is the growth here,
and I tell myself, look, in the center, here, I first simply have an epiblastic tissue
about flat.
Then, very quickly, we notice that this epiblastic tissue takes on an S shape.
I position myself right in the center here, and I observe that the cells that are right
in the axis here of the center,
that are here, you see, the cells that are there, do not grow at the same speed, just there.
And what do I see emerging? A movement like this,
that the upper part grows, grows like
this,
and begins to grow and do this.
And what is this?
Because here we just have
a cut like this
so here
is a point
as we have called point 0
this is the part that grows
so just imagine it's there, that's a wave
Well, it's a multiplication of cells, it's an accelerated mitosis that does like this.
And what will happen?
Look closely, this will create, here underneath, a
type of tube.
And this tube is the process of gastrulation, it's called the notochord.
At this stage, Henson's node is the tip of the notochord.
are the same. At this stage, there is a movement
back here we call Henson's node
which moves backward, from cranial to caudal. And
here, it's a point where it doesn’t move.
And here, in this movement, you have the development of the primitive cranio-sacral axis.
This means that this system, it is not yet neuronal, it's neuro
-coronal.
This means that my notochord, the tip of my notochord, if you look, you will see in other diagrams, c
it's my skull base.
This will be the future space for the development of my skull base.
And Henson's node here in the back, is where my sacrum will develop.
At Henson’s node.
Yes, because many people confuse Henson's node with the closure
of the posterior notochord.
And that has nothing to do with it!
But where is the adult Henson's node?
The remnant, you find it on the sacrum.
You see the sacrum, like this.
You have C1, you have S1, S2,
and you have the notochord that comes here.
That comes here.
So sacrum, S1, S2, S3, S4.
And you have the notochord descending there.
What we call the vestige.
It's a notochord and here what do I have? I have my cul-de-sac of Douglas
point zero and Henson's node have differentiated initially they are together
initially they are together the future skull base with the sacrum?
No, I am together, you see, and then all of a sudden
actually it’s not
that they are really separated it’s a wave of growth with a fixed point
which is my skull base
system that goes down below.
And that's where I have
a fixed point and a mobile point.
And when I spoke to you this morning, I told you
that the sacrum is a
mobile fulcrum and my base
of the skull is a fixed fulcrum.
Blechschmidt,
in classical embryology
talks about a process of
gastrulation. But the
gastrulation, it comes from a term
that comes from amphibians.
Blechschmidt, he says no, I
I don't want to talk about gastrulation, I want to talk about an axial process.
And he explains the establishment of this axial process.
This is a section, and we see it like a section like this, you see.
It's the S, you see.
So where is the point zero?
You come below, my dear, hop, there, and you are the point zero.
What is the algorithm?
It tells us the part in the dome of ex...
expansion compared to my dome of retention, it will grow much faster.
But you imagine that it is in a space like this, where is my embryonic pedicle
located?
So the trophic information arrives here.
And I make a movement like this.
And here, inside, I have...
I have a tube taking shape.
This is how a primitive axial process develops.
This is how primitively, I have the cranio-sacral axis starting to develop.
The sacral point is not there yet, but it will arrive here.
It will arrive there.
I'm just showing you a dynamic, an axis.
So it goes like this.
The movement with point zero.
with this dome that comes over here
this is point zero and point zero
is the same
at the moment I have this wave
it's point zero
even when I have the S
it's point zero, so yes, but not ultimately
but it does show that the sacrum
and the occiput in the future
in fact it's a functional unit
they are made
of a movement
so when we take that sacrum there
In fact, we are directly connected through this process to my skull base.
This kind of movement, like this, with my finger inside here.
And we see here a remnant of my notochord.
My notochord comes here.
It goes up to my skull base.
I draw that the notochord, skull base,
all the vertebrae, up to the level of my terminal part, at the level of the
sacrum.
But the point that doesn't move is not at the extremity, it was in the center, back there, at the bottom.
Yes, but you will see in the later development of the embryo,
at this stage, we can say that the anterior part of the embryo that
is here, you see,
so my node is there, here, and well all this is your head,
and just a small part, is your trunk.
After, it will change shape.
This will develop very strongly, this less.
But at this stage, it was there, right in the middle of the embryo.
My fixed point, and the rolling behind.
The occiput will develop here, the sacrum develops there.
It's in the other direction, yes, compared to the skull too.
And the notochord, it's more than at the beginning.
My vertebrae, my neural tube, and there, what do I have?
I have my notochord.
in the vertebrae and ultimately what will it become in the embryonic disk
what
will remain beyond the process but the axis is there in
the beginning that’s why I told you
when treating disc issues you need to see what is happening in
the mouth since the base
of the skull that is the tip of my primitive notochord will be organized
organized by my occlusion, my notochord.
This is my hypophyseal cartilage.
What will become of the hypophyseal cartilage?
It will become the body of the sphenoid.
What will become of the paracordal cartilage that is there?
Paracordal will become the basilar part of my occipital bone.
And there, what is this? What do we call this?
The SSB.
What is the name of this whole set of stories here?
There, the skull base.
The difficulty is that you have to see it in three dimensions.
At the moment when I have this notochordal process being established,
that is, I have this establishment of this wave of
mitotic construction,
of this development, a little will appear at the level of my embryonic pedicle
of...
axis we call the primitive streak which is an energy field of aspiration
that appears
and from that movement we will see above that my epiblast will
transform into ectoderm but
for this by this aspiration movement there will be a lateral traction
that's this movement
if you imagine I see the large growth of my dome part
Here, I see here a primitive streak appearing.
Here, I have this dome that will form my Henson's node
which moves backward here, like this, you see, by growth.
At the same time, in this phase of development,
the cells that are here laterally will be pulled toward the center
through the process of growth.
And the epiblast which is...
the center will come, will form
the cells here that will meet
you see, will
tighten like this, you see
and they will become
a bottle cell, we call
bottle cells, you see, look above
it's written, bottle cells
and they will be sucked in
between my tissue
that you mentioned earlier, but what happens to
my tissue
below, well between the two
there is a space that opens
And in this space, there is a field of aspiration
where cells will arrive and will form the primitive mesoderm.
That is to say, when I have this third cavity appearing,
I have this notochordal process being initiated,
which will create the third tissue,
which we call ectoderm, mesoderm, endoderm.
And this is where the mesoderm will appear.
And so this is how we see that in this...
process, you see, from my primitive streak and the displacement of my notochord, we
see
cells beginning to be pulled towards the center to fill the
intermediate tissue which will form what we call the primitive mesoblast, which we call
the
future mesoderm. So it is the epiblastic tissue that will
give rise to the mesoderm and
it is the epiblastic tissue that will give rise to the notochord. We see the wave arriving
it's really a wave in fact
it's like a wave
you really have to see it like this
the tube there
is created it’s my notochord
and here is my Henson's node
and there is a primitive streak that Blechschmidt does not describe
at the moment
when I have this process appearing
already
the mesoderm begins to form
and it's happening simultaneously
but at the same moment
again in this story
Behind here, there is a magnificent observation of a nodal flow that breaks the symmetry of the embryo on a molecular plane.
So what is happening?
A few years ago, we wondered, but why is the heart on the left, why is it on the right,
why all this is inverted, etc.
At the time of this wave back here, if we look further down,
we enter...
and see that there are little cilia that move, but there is a liquid, which we call
nodal liquid,
which becomes a nodal flow. I see this wave.
I can go up and see what’s happening, but quite closely.
And I see that on this tissue, there are little cilia that move.
And then they noticed that these cilia do not make a forward-backward movement,
they make a movement.
circular. So it turns and always brings things
from right to
left. In observation, they realized it was tilted at 60 degrees,
at 23
degrees or 60 degrees. When it turns, when it moves away here, when it turns,
it accelerates. It does that. And so it brings about
ultimately a preferential flow.
And above,
on the cells, you have actually a little snow falling,
which are small morphogenetic molecules.
So these are small vesicles that contain lots of proteins, and which are
brought at that moment by the flow from right to left.
And these little flurries, we are in micros, clash.
It releases a whole tissue, a whole different protein activity
that creates the asymmetry of the embryo.
Because these are pre-morphogenetic molecules that will at some point inform the heart and develop the information.
This means that at the moment when I have the axial process, I have a left side, a right side,
a top side and a bottom side that appear.
And at the same time, I have a specific axis
and through these moments
I have all the mesoderm tissue that appears
and in addition I have a whole activity
morphogenetic
sorry, asymmetric morphogenetic
that develops
and I have my primitive cranio-sacral axis
arriving
and well it starts between the 14th
and the 21st day
alright